# Ryan Madden

8 Devonshire Drive, White Plains, NY 10605~rmadden514@gmail.com ~(914) 924-3970

### INTRODUCTION

Summa cum Laude graduate of SUNY Binghamton (2013) with a BA in Political Science and Environmental Studies. Strong passion for environmental sustainability, renewable energy, and climate change action. Have worked in public outreach, grass roots organizing, and campaigning in the environmental and political sphere since 2008. Proficient in public speaking, leading outreach initiatives, conducting political canvassing, and networking.

### SELECTED ACCOMPLISHMENTS

- Promoted the Energy Leadership Program of Cornell Cooperative Extension: Broome County for two semesters as a student of Binghamton University. Hired upon graduation to be the lead intern for the Summer 2013 program. Presented to various organizations during this time; conducted case management with clients enrolled in the program; sustained lines of communication with energy providers, building contractors, and financial institutions to assist clients throughout the program. Attended 20 presentations and tabling events, leading to the enrollment of over 100 clients in the program.
- Conducted graduate-level research in civil conflict management and peace studies at the University of North Texas. Authored a paper entitled "Judicial Independence and Peace Duration: An Assessment of Political Institutions in the Post-Conflict Environment" which was published in *The Eagle Feather: A Publication for Undergraduate Scholars*. Presented the research at the Midwest Political Science Association Conference in Chicago in April of 2013.
- Elected to be President of Binghamton College Democrats. Held weekly club meetings; coordinated events and rallies; campaigned on behalf of local, state, and federal politicians; and collaborated with various student organizations. Registered hundreds of students on campus to vote; sent petitions to NY state officials; and increased club membership.
- Elected to be Regional Chairman of Central New York for College Democrats of New York. Facilitated communication between College Democrats chapters at universities in my region. Organized campaign events for various congressional districts and established voter registration drives on campuses. Planned the College Democrats of New York Annual Convention in 2011 at Syracuse University.
- Selected to be a youth delegate for the 19th Session of the Conference of Parties (COP) to the United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change, taking place in November 2013 in Warsaw, Poland. Delegates work prior to the conference to develop policy priorities, acquire skills in effective lobbying, and engage the broader youth community in action related to international climate policy. At the COP, members work alongside government delegates, leaders from international organizations, and fellow members of civil society to ensure a just and progressive outcome to the negotiations.
- Shadowed a child with Asperger syndrome in the summer of 2011. Ensured the child's comfort throughout all daily activities, while accommodating any needs he had. Helped child overcome reservations with socializing during athletic situations. He was actively participating in camp activities by the end of the summer.
- Studied Spanish language for 8 years throughout high school and college. Spent 5 months living with a Spanish family in Valencia in 2012 during a study abroad program. Obtained a conversational proficiency in speaking, writing, and reading. Comfortable utilizing Spanish in business situations.

### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

September 2012-Present Energy Leadership Program

Binghamton, NY

The Energy Leadership Program is a program that seeks to promote home energy efficiency, local job creation, and environmental sustainability to Southern Tier residents, non-profits, small businesses and organizations.

Lead Intern (Paid)
Intern

(6/13-present) (9/12-5/13)

June 2012-July 2012 National Science Foundation Research Program

Denton, Texas

The Department of Political Science at the University of North Texas conducts a program to provide undergraduate students from across the country the opportunity to engage in graduate-level research in conflict management and peace science during the summer that integrates training in civil conflict management with training in computer simulation skills. Participants use computer simulation software to develop theoretical propositions that are tested empirically. Participants collect and analyze empirical data and report their findings in a public forum. Activities include workshops on theory development, computer simulations, and research methodology.

### **Undergraduate Researcher**

July 2011-August 2011 White Plains Department of Recreation

White Plains, NY

The White Plains Department of Recreation operates a series of programs and services, including a summer day camp at White Plains High School called Camp Quarropas. This program includes accommodations for special needs children. Special needs counselors are hired upon recommendation and are required to go through extra screening beforehand.

## **Special Needs Counselor**

### **EDUCATION**

**Binghamton University, State University of New York**, Vestal, New York Harpur College of Arts & Sciences

## BA in Political Science, Minor in Environmental Studies, May 2013

Graduated summa cum laude

Recipient of Henry H. Bauer Award for Excellence in Political Science Inductee to Phi Beta Kappa

**AIP Language Institute**, Valencia, Spain, January 2012-May 2012 Study Abroad Semester

### **PERSONAL**

22 years of age Single Excellent health Interests include current events, cinema, tennis, and politics Willing to travel/relocate

### REFERENCES

Will be furnished upon request